[SPEAKER_00]: Ajahn, I diligently observed the eight precepts and I believe I'm putting in sincere effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, a persistent thought troubles me.
[SPEAKER_00]: The notion that using or having money might impede my progress or purity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is refraining from money one of the higher precepts, the ten precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: How does abstaining from it contribute to spiritual freedom?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's inherently wrong with money?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because as long as I use it for good and refrain from harmful actions, could money be a hindrance to awakening?
[SPEAKER_01]: In short, no, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it was a practical reason for that precept.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the order grew, basically, you know, like you have monks on their own, ordaining here and there, through various teachers,
[SPEAKER_01]: Living roughly, traveling around, having access to money, meant having access to essential things, if that's where their mind would turn towards.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it was a practical rule to prevent the temptations for new monks, for monks that are not developed, for monks that are not established in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, even today as well, you could think about it, like, if you were to have your own money without any supervision,
[SPEAKER_01]: Without anybody else knowing how it's being spent, if the mind is not developed, you might give in to desires and get this or get that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's, again, if you're not developed, if you're not interested in practice, if you're slacking, if you're regressing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in a similar fashion, it was like a, you know, the rule about not storing food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, it was for those who are not developed,
[SPEAKER_01]: To prevent them from kind of going lax and and proliferating towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because it's in and of itself an impediment for enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, Arahant broke that rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was an Arahant who was storing food, not because out of desire or craving, but because the village was too poor.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they couldn't... they... they would still feed him, but he felt bad for taking food every day, because they don't have enough for themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if he had the leftover, he would put it aside to eat next day, so he doesn't take it from them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, the Buddha said, no, it's an offense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You got to convey.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, from a practical standpoint of an managing the order of monks, it could give rise that allowance to like many monks.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were not arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were not developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could basically, because of that, start slacking and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the money was the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, who has access to money, has access to the five codes of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, back in the day, like, you could have engaged with those things without anybody ever knowing, because there were so many different summoners, different brahmins, different types, somebody had money, somebody not, nobody would have batten an eyelid, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they would have made that rule, just to prevent those who are not developed, who are still in training, to kind of fall into that trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, it applies to the monks.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have withdrawn yourself from everything else, eh... given up the household life,
[SPEAKER_01]: Having that kind of direct, untracked access to money can become the impediment there, there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're a householder, keeping the precepts, eight precepts, great, practicing within that, again, if you keep the precepts, no amount of money can become an obstacle for you, unless you break the precepts through money.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you start... or sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are well restrained, restraining your senses, restraining your craving, again, no amount of gold or money can make you lose that perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, as if you are, like, from the standpoint of managing an order, if something like that happens, you have to look at the bigger picture, and then say, ah, no, because, again, for most of these new monks or something, it could result in issues.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's just not even go there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this is not that... it's not the same context.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the same... it's not the same starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: What about that whole, you know, once you... if you have money, okay, you have access to sensual pleasures of all kinds.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you... you also... or some people would have a sense of control, of safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of safety, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but see, that's... money just reveals that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was gonna...
[SPEAKER_01]: I was gonna say that next.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if that person who asked the question...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if they're a monk or a layman, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they're a monk...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think they're a layperson.
[SPEAKER_00]: Presumably a layperson, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, money would not be an obstacle for arahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being a householder would be an obstacle for arahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, if you're not even a sotāpanna, or anāgāmī from that point of view, I wouldn't worry about obstacle, last obstacle for arahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: Develop everything else that you can, as opposed to now taking too much and not even doing the first step properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the reason why, as I said, money would reveal that sense of control, sense of control that's inherently bound with a household life.
[SPEAKER_01]: I come as I please.
[SPEAKER_01]: I go as I please.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm my own boss.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody tells me what to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody tells me how to walk, how to talk, how to eat, how to carry my ball, how to relate to people.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can just do what I want, because I'm an individual.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have my own place, my own apartment, my own house.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm my own boss.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that, inherently, is bound with the sense of control and sense of safety that comes from Kali.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why a layman cannot become an Arahant from that point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because there's some magical energy preventing him, but because, to that degree, he's still not relinquishing that sense of control that's founded upon his sense of I Am.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like I need to magically put the robes on in order to become an Arahant then.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to relinquish the household life, regardless of what I wear.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to relinquish that fundamental control that I've been living through my whole life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's really the issue there, not the money.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're keeping the eight precepts, and are diligent in regard to it, and diligent in sense restraint, develop the right view, free yourself from sensuality within that, money will then just be a practical tool you're using for survival, because you're not... you're not going around on pindapad or getting food by donors and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, like, if you want to really become an arahant and you don't have anybody depending on you in your life, they would die if you leave and so on, how it was back in the suttas, then go forth, ordain and give up the money as well and there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now it's like worrying about what type of cart do I have when you haven't even found a horse.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's, it's, you know, one step at a time.